<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon shewing the meanes how we may escape the damnation of Hell. To which end it was preached and is published by N.B.</title>
            <author>Basely, N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E579_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 89:E579[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon shewing the meanes how we may escape the damnation of Hell. To which end it was preached and is published by N.B.</title>
                  <author>Basely, N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich: Royston at the Angel in Ivie-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XL. XI. [1651, i.e. 1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>N. B. = N. Basely.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: 1649.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou. 9".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON, SHEWING The Meanes how we may Eſcape the Damnation of HELL.</p>
            <p>To which end it was Preached and is Publiſhed by N.B.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE 12. v. 5.</bibl>
               <p>I will forewarne you whom yee ſhall Feare: Feare Him, who after He hath killed, hath power to caſt into Hell; yea, I ſay unto you, Feare Him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for Rich: Royſton at the Angel in Ivie-lane. M.DC.XL.XI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:117580:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117580:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. c. 23. v. 33.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How can Ye eſcape the Damnation of Hell?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Verſe begins thus: <hi>Ye Serpents, ye gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers.</hi> A very ſtrange compella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in reſpect of Him, from whom it did proceed. For though they to whom this was ſpoken, might juſtly deſerve it; yet it may ſeem ſtrange, that ſuch a ſpeech ſhould proceed out of our Saviours mouth: that He who bids us learn of Him, to be, as He is, <hi>meek and lowely in heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> ſhould utter this ſpeech, which ſeemes to ſavour of nothing leſſe than meekneſſe. For, what more baſe than the Serpent, which crawles on the earth and licks the duſt? What more deteſtable than the Viper, which gnaweth out the bowels of her that bred him? Theſe were creatures, to which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour reſembles the Scribes and Phariſees: to the craftie Serpent and to the ungratefull Viper: which as they are full of poyſon; ſo they are the lively emblemes of deceipt and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>But this ſpeech was juſt and fitting, both in reſpect of <hi>Him</hi> that ſpake it; and of <hi>Them,</hi> to whom it was ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is not doubt but that they to whom this was ſpoken did juſtly deſerve, that it ſhould be ſpoken to them. For, they were not onely <hi>a ſinfull nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>a people laden with iniquity;</hi> as they were in the daies of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> But now they had even filled up the meaſure of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers iniquities, in killing the Prophets, and ſtoning thoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117580:3"/>that were ſent unto them: And therefore this reprehenſion, how ſharp ſoever, could not be too bitter for ſuch vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Serpents, ſuch ungratefull Vipers.</p>
            <p>But of this there is little doubt, but this ſpeech was moſt juſt in reſpect of Them, to whom it was ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The queſtion is, How this could agree with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours meekneſſe; and how farre we may imitate Him herein? For the cleering whereof we muſt conſider, that Chriſt being both God and Man, did perfectly know not onely what they were, diſcerning the preſent thoughts and intentions of their hears: but alſo by His all-ſeeing wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as He was God, knew what they would be: that they would not onely not repent of what they had done; but moreover would fill up the meaſure of their iniquities, by crucifying Him the Lord of life: knowing their diſeaſe to be thus grievous, He applies this corroſive &amp; ſmarting plaiſter, to free them from that horrible torment of the damnation of Hell. It did not proceed from any the leaſt diſturbance or paſſion of our Saviour; but onely from a tender care of their recovery and welfare to whom He ſpake.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe, who from this example of our Saviour would take a liberty to themſelves to uſe the like ſharp language to them, whom they reprove for their ſinnes, I would adviſe them to conſider, Whether Chriſt, who is ſaid to have taught the people,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lat. 7.29.</note> 
               <hi>as one having authority,</hi> and not as their uſuall Doctors, be to be imitated in this, which ſeems to be a thing extraordinary, grounded upon Chriſt's all-ſeeing knowledge, as he was God as well as Man. And if they object,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.7.</note> that <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> uſed the like ſpeech to theſe Phariſees and Sadduces; I would have them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt</hi> was <hi>a Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 11.9.</note> 
               <hi>yea and more than a Prophet.</hi> And therefore till they can aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of God's Spirit in ſuch a plentifull meaſure, they ſhall doe well, in my judgement, to uſe ſuch charitable and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly compellations, as the Apoſtles and Primitive Fathers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117580:3"/>uſe to their hearers. As for my ſelfe, I ſhall not preſume to take to me this liberty, how lawfull ſoever; eſpecially to you, of whoſe love to God and care of your owne ſoules I am very well perſwaded: But in all Chriſtian love and meekneſſe aske of you onely this neceſſary queſtion: 4 <hi>How can ye</hi> 3 <hi>Eſcape the</hi> 2 <hi>Damnation of</hi> 1 <hi>Hell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which queſtion, that we may fully underſtand &amp; ſo be the better able to make a ſatisfying anſwer to our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: we will conſider theſe foure things, as parts which doe plainly ariſe from, and fully comprehend the whole ſubſtance of the Text:
<list>
                  <item>1. That there is a Hell.</item>
                  <item>2. That there is a Damnation of Hell.</item>
                  <item>3. That we may Eſcape that damnation.</item>
                  <item>4. How we may eſcape it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The two former of which are ſuch manifeſt truths, ſo generally acknowledged of all Chriſtians: that it were needleſſe to prove that there is a Hell, and a Damnation of that hell; but onely as the knowledge and conſideration of theſe may ſerve as a meanes How we may eſcape the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Hell.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">I. That there is a Hell, is a truth, which no Chriſtian will deny, who profeſſeth to believe (and I hope believes as he profeſſeth) that Chriſt for us men and for our ſalvation deſcended into Hell. For, howſoever among the learned there be ſome diſſent in opinion concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of His deſcent, and alſo concerning the <hi>cauſe</hi> why He deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thither: yet all agree about the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelfe, that He deſcended into Hell. And that agreement of theirs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the diſagreement about the manner and cauſe of His deſcent prove plainly that He deſcended into Hell. For, why ſhould they contend about the manner how, and the cauſe why He deſcended into Hell, if He did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend thither? It is a good and ſound argument uſed by a holy and learned Father of our Church, to prove, that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117580:4"/>Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> was univerſally obſerved by all Chriſtians; becauſe there was ſuch a generall contention about the-time of celebrating it: <hi>Becauſe that muſt Be, which muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for.</hi> And the ſame will hold in this caſe very well. They that ſo earneſtly contend about the cauſe and manner of our Saviour's deſcending into Hell, doe by that their contention confeſſe, that they believe that He deſcended into Hell: and that neceſſarily ſuppoſeth that there is a Hell, into which He did deſcend. This is a thing which all Chriſtians believe.</p>
               <p>And no mervaile if they doe ſo: Seeing this is common to them, not onely with the Turks and other Mahometans; who as they believe a Paradiſe (though a moſt fooliſh one) for thoſe of their owne ſuperſtition: ſo they believe that there is a Hell, a place of unſufferable torments for thoſe, who in their opinion do either believe amiſſe, or ſpend their lives in much wickedneſſe: But the very Pagans themſelves do acknowledge a place of torments allotted to the wicked after this life. The writings of their Philoſophers and Poets make often mention of it. And though the deſcription, which they make thereof be fabulous, and diſagreeing from each other: Yet we know that nothing is ſo fabulous, but that it hath it's foundation from ſome truth: And as for their diſagreement in the deſcription of it, it is the leſſe to be admired in them; ſeeing the Chriſtian Doctors are of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry opinions concerning the place and other circumſtances thereof. But as for the thing it ſelfe, all, Jewes, Chriſtians, Mahometans, Pagans, all agree in the maine point, that there is a Hell, a place where wicked and ungodly men are puniſhed for the ſinnes, which they have committed in this life. In this the Heathens writings and the Holy-Scriptures doe not diſagree, that there is a place of torments, that there is a Hell. The Heathen Philoſopher <hi>Plato</hi> doth not much diſagree with <hi>Juſtine Martyr</hi> the Chriſtian Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and the other Fathers, in the deſcription of Hell. But that there is a place of unconceivable torments prepared
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117580:4"/>for the wicked, in this they all agree: That as there are joyes in Heaven for thoſe that have lived well; ſo there is a Hell for the ungodly.</p>
               <p>As many as doe acknowledge that God is juſt, and that the ſoule is immortall, muſt needs believe that there is a place of puniſhment after this life, for thoſe ſoules, which have lived wickedly in this life. I am perſwaded that no man who believes that there is a God, will deny that there is a Hell. A lewd man indeed, who is guilty to himſelfe of much wickedneſſe, may <hi>wiſh</hi> that there were neither God nor Hell to puniſh him for his wickedneſſe: and ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires often reiterated may multiply into a perſwaſion that ſo it is; that there is neither God nor Hell. But the moſt wicked man that is, though he deny it by his life; yet he cannot chuſe but believe in his heart, that there is a place where his wicked deeds ſhall receive their juſt reward.</p>
               <p>For their ſakes therefore I hold it expedient, not to prove that there is a Hell; but in a more compendious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable way to ſhew you what this Hell is, in ſuch manner as the Antients have deſcribed it unto us. That ſo the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of the horrour of that place may deterre us from doing that, which may bring us into it.</p>
               <p>I have either heard or read of one, who beholding a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, where the torments of the damned were lively repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, the ſight thereof cauſed him to forſake his former evill courſes; and to ſpend the reſt of his life virtuouſly. Of another, who ſeeing a picture, where <hi>Corah</hi> and his ſeditious company were ſwallowed up alive by the earth, for rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> conſidering the horrour of that puniſhment, deſiſted from ſome trayterous enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, which he had conceived in his heart. Perhaps the conſideration of this dreadfull place, occaſioned by our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe thereof, may ſo farre worke upon ſome, that they deſiſt from their accuſtomed ſinnes; leſt they alſo come into this place of torment. For, certainly a ſoveraigne meanes to prevent comming into Hell both in body and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117580:5"/>ſoule, is, Often to deſcend thither in our thoughts and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations: that by often thinking of it, we may never feele it.</p>
               <p>It is written of the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> that they would not ſo much as once name the Devill: ſuch deteſtation they pretended to have of him and all his works: Which I doe not blame in them; as ſuppoſing it to proceed from a ſincere love of piety. But ſure it cannot but be a very profitable thing for a Chriſtian, Often to think upon Hell: That thoſe whom Heaven cannot allure to the love of virtue, the feare of Hell may deterre from ſinne.</p>
               <p>The learned among the Heathen, who have written of this ſubject, doe deſcribe it in ſuch manner, that they leave nothing unſaid, which the wit and malice of a mercileſſe Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant could invent to torture a miſerable Offender. The puniſhment of <hi>Aridaeus</hi> the Tyrant of <hi>Pamphilia,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other villanies, murthered his owne Father and Brother, is very lively deſcribed by <hi>Plato:</hi> The wit of man cannot invent more dreadfull torments, than this wicked Tyrant is feigned to have ſuffered in Hell.</p>
               <p>But the Chriſtian Doctors, grounding their opinion upon the laſt words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to which our Saviour ſeems to allude, <hi>Marke</hi> 9.44. expreſſe the paines of Hell by <hi>Fire;</hi> as that which of all other things doth cauſe the greateſt paine. But this you muſt obſerve, that when they name <hi>Fire,</hi> they meane not ſuch as is common with us; but ſuch a terrible fire, as this with us ſcarce warme in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that. That fornace which <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> made ſo hot, that the flame thereof is ſaid to have aſcended nine and fourty cubits high, was but as a hot-bath in reſpect of this. The paines of Hell are ſuch, that we may goe about to ſhaddow them out by ſome ſuch things, as are moſt terrible to us: but fully to conceive of them as they are indeed, is altogether impoſſible. When we tell you of a ſtinking and darke Lake burning with brimſtome, in which nothing were to be heard, but onely the furious raging of helliſh Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117580:5"/>and horrible lamentation of damned perſons; this is onely to expreſſe unto you thoſe torments, which cannot ſufficiently be conceived as they are indeed. God forbid that any of us ſhould ever know what the paines of Hell are: which none can know, but onely they that ſuffer them. For when you have thought upon all thoſe hideous torments, which ſhall be inflicted on the wicked, both in their bodies and all the ſenſes and members thereof, and in their ſoules and all the faculties thereof: yet this may ſeem tolerable in compariſon of another kind of torment, which ſhall befall the wicked; which the learned call the paine of <hi>Loſſe:</hi> which is to be deprived for ever and ever of the bleſſed ſight of God and his holy Angels and Saints, and of thoſe unſpeakable joyes, which they partake with God. This is the Loſſe of all loſſes: So great a torment to the damned, that it is not poſſible for any man to expreſſe by words the exceeding greatneſſe of this grief. So great it is, that Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, That if a thouſand fires of hell were joyned together in one, they ſhould never be ſo great a paine to the ſoule, as it is for the ſoule to be ſeparated in this wiſe for ever from Almighty God. The finall doome of the wicked is this, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.27. <hi>Depart from me all ye workers of iniquity.</hi> Onely this, <hi>Depart from me:</hi> preſently followes, <hi>There ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, when ye ſhall ſee</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the Prophets in the Kingdome of God, and you your ſelves thrust out. Weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> for what themſelves ſuffer: <hi>Gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> for indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation that others enjoy the happineſſe, which they have loſt, and might have obtained. This is it which torments them with unſpeakable griefe.</p>
               <p>Now if you adde hereunto, that theſe unconceivable paines, both of <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>loſſe,</hi> ſhall never have an end; that after many thouſands of yeares are paſt, a Sinner is no nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the end of his torments, than he was the very firſt houre, that he entred into them: This cannot chuſe but ſtrike the moſt hard heart that is into horrour: When he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117580:6"/>ſhall conſider, that if all the lives of all creatures, that have been from the beginning of the world, with all thoſe that ſhall be to the end of it, were (as I may ſay) ſpun into one life; it would be as nothing in reſpect of <hi>Eternitie.</hi> When you meditate (as I hope you often doe) upon the paines of Hell; doe but ſeriouſly thinke upon this one word <hi>Ever:</hi> and you need ſay no more to expreſſe the paines of Hell; that they are endleſſe;<note place="margin">Mar. 9.44.</note> 
                  <hi>That their worme dieth not, neither is their fire quenched.</hi> It is the property of this fire, ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that it doth alwaies preſerve: And thoſe that are puniſhed with it, doe ſo die, that they doe alwaies live. As the leaſt paine in Hell is much more grievous, than all the torments, that can be ſuffered here on earth: So the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> of thoſe paines, and the continuall remembrance of it, is more terrible than all thoſe paines, be they never ſo many and grievous.</p>
               <p>I will not ſo much wrong this Chriſtian audience, as to go about to prove this truth unto you; that the paines of hell are <hi>Endleſſe:</hi> That were to accuſe you as either not knowing or not believing that, which the very Heathen did acknowledge. To ſignifie this, they feigned one to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about continually in a wheele; another to role a ſtone to the top of an hill, which ſtill returned back upon him; others to fill a bottomleſſe tub with water; another to have his liver devoured by a Vulture all the day long, and in the night-time to grow againe, that it might alwaies be eaten, but never conſumed. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſeemes to make the like alluſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14. <hi>They lie in hell like ſheep, death gnaweth on them.</hi> Signifying, that as the graſſe which is eaten by the cattell; ſpringeth and groweth againe; becauſe the root thereof, which is the beginning of life, ſtill liveth: So the damned, being alwaies fed upon by the devouring fire, ſhall never die: becauſe their ſoule, the principall fuell of this fire, is immortall. Such as their ſoule is, ſuch ſhall be their torments, immortall and endleſſe. The paſture of this field is immortall: though it be alwaies eaten, it alwaies ſpringeth againe.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117580:6"/>
               <p>If you demand how it can ſtand with God's juſtice to puniſh a <hi>finite ſinne</hi> with an <hi>infinite puniſhment?</hi> Why he who hath ſinned a <hi>few</hi> yeares, ſhould ſuffer <hi>eternall</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? I anſwer, that this dealing of God with impenitent ſinners is moſt juſt: not onely in reſpect of God, againſt whom they have ſinned; whoſe Perſon is infinite; and therefore the ſinne againſt Him deſerves the like puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; an infinite juſtice to be ſatisfied by an infinite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But even in reſpect of the Sinner himſelfe, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ought to be eternall. For, the paines of Hell are proportioned not only to the <hi>act</hi> of a Sinner, which he <hi>hath done;</hi> but to his <hi>will,</hi> what he <hi>would have done,</hi> if he might have lived for ever. And then what wonder is it, if he that would have ſinned againſt God everlaſtingly, if it had been in his power; be everlaſtingly puniſhed by God, who hath power ſo to doe? God does by him no otherwiſe, than he would doe by God: Neither are the torments of Hell more grievous to man; than the ſinnes of man are offenſive to God. Sinne is as much diſpleaſing to the eſſence of God, as torment is grievous to the nature of man. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no mervaile it is, if God puniſh that with infinite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is infinitely diſpleaſing to Him? For, in Hell the condition of the ſinne and of the Sinner ſeeme to be ſomewhat alike, in this reſpect; that as the ſinne may alwaies de puniſhed, but never cleanſed: ſo neither ſhall the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their body ever be ended, nor the body be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. There the damned ſhall ever live to die, and ever die to live. That as there are eternall joyes prepared in heaven for thoſe that love and ſerve God: ſo there are everlaſting torments ordained in Hell for thoſe that diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Him. Which is the Damnation here ſpoken of: <hi>How can ye Eſcape the Damnation of Hell?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="2">II. Having ſhewed you not onely that there is a Hell, but what this Hell is; I need not ſtand to prove that there is a Damnation of this Hell: that will follow by a neceſſary
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117580:7"/>conſequence. No houſe is built, but for ſome Inhabitant; no puniſhment is prepared, but for ſome Offender: If there neither were nor would be Malefactors, it were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to build any Priſons. God would never have made Hell, but that in his infinite wiſdome he foreſaw that there would be ſome, who would deſerve it, how intolerable ſo ever it were. There have been, and are ſome ſo malitious and obſtinate in their ſinnes, that Hell it ſelfe, if it were not infinitely miſerable, were not miſerable enough to puniſh them for their wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>The Heathen who did acknowledge a Hell, did believe that there was a Condemnation of all ſuch, as had lived wickedly in this life. Thoſe three Kings, <hi>Aeacus, Minos,</hi> and <hi>Radamanthus,</hi> who were famous for their juſtice here on earth, were therefore feigned to have been Judges in the other world; and to have rewarded each man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſerts: the virtuous with faire <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields, and the wicked with burning and ſtinking rivers. For, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many who had committed notorious wickedneſſe, as murder, adultery, rapine, and the like haynous offences, not onely to ſuffer no puniſhment in this life, but even to enjoy great proſperity all their life long; they did conclude (as well they might) that there was ſome time and place, when and where God would execute upon them the effects of His juſtice, and reward them according to their doings.</p>
               <p>This opinion of theirs is very agreeable to the Chriſtian doctrine, which teacheth that <hi>juſtice</hi> is as proper to God as <hi>mercy:</hi> that as by the one he doth reward the Godly with the joyes of Heaven; ſo by the other, he doth puniſh the Wicked with the eternall torments of Hell and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paravit coelum, ſed paravit &amp; tartarum, &amp;c.</hi> God, ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> hath prepared heaven, but he hath alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared hell, (the one for the good, the other for the bad.) He hath prepared everlaſting reſt; but he hath alſo prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red everlaſting torments: He hath prepared unconceivable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117580:7"/>light; but he hath alſo prepared the unſpeakable darkneſſe of a perpetuall night. As there are good and bad; ſheep and goates: ſo there is heaven and hell. Unto the eternall joyes of the one the good are mercifully Elected: unto the endleſſe miſeries of the other the wicked are juſtly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. The Catholique Faith admits of a juſt Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the pains of hell, as well as of a mercifull Election to the joyes of heaven. Whereof the one depends on Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> the other on his <hi>juſtice:</hi> And they that deny either the one or the other of theſe two eſtates, doe rob God of one of his eſſentiall properties.</p>
               <p>If you aske me, <hi>Who</hi> they are that ſhall ſuffer this <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of hell? I will tell you in brief not only <hi>who</hi> they are, but alſo <hi>why</hi> they are <hi>Damned.</hi> Who they are that ſhall ſuffer theſe paines of hell? the Prophet <hi>David</hi> tells us in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall terms, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into hell, and all the people that forget God.</hi> All wicked and impenitent Sinners ſhall be Damned; becauſe they forget God, and neglect to ſerve Him, and fulfill his commands. But to ſpeak more particularly; The firſt that was caſt into hell was <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer:</hi> And the cauſe <hi>why,</hi> was his <hi>diſobedience of God,</hi> ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from his abominable <hi>pride.</hi> The Devil was the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell; and for that rebellion loſt his part in the unconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able joyes of heaven; and ſuffered the eternall paines of hell: And they that take part with him in that or any other ſinne, ſhall be ſure to ſuffer the ſame puniſhment, that he and his Angels doe. <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> That is the doom of the wicked pronounced by our Saviour at the laſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as you may ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. It was <hi>prepared for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> even all thoſe that diſobey God's commands, and preferre their owne will before His. For, <hi>The whole and onely cauſe of Damnation,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian, is (Perverſa adminiſtratio conditionis à conditis) the ill-managing of the Creation by the Creatures:</hi> that they are the things of this world, not according to God's commands, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117580:8"/>to their owne will. Which gave juſt occaſion to one of the antient Fathers to ſay, <hi>That nothing doth burne in hell, ſo much as the ſtuborne will of a Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hence it is, that the ſinne of an obſtinate and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent mind is puniſhed eternally, although committed in time, and that perhaps a ſhort time; becauſe that which was ſhort in acting, was long in reſpect of his ſtuborne will. So that if ſuch Sinners ſhould never die, they would never leave off to ſinne; yea, they would alwaies live, that they might alwaies ſinne. As in this life they would not ceaſe from ſinne; although God did exhort, threaten, intreat, and uſe all meanes poſſible: So in the other life God will not leave off to puniſh them, although they howle and lament grievouſly.</p>
               <p>But that which makes the torments of the Damned to be endleſſe, is a continuall hatred which they have of Almighty God, whoſe juſtice thus puniſheth them. And as long as they continue to hate God, what mervaile is it, if God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere to puniſh them? As their ſinne is, ſo likewiſe is their puniſhment without any end. Then ſhall that be truly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, which is written, <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.6. <hi>In thoſe daies ſhall men ſeek death, and ſhall not find it; and ſhall deſire to die, and death ſhall flee from them.</hi> Never was ſleep ſo welcome to a drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie head,<note place="margin">Jer. 51.57.</note> as death (ſuch as the Prophet <hi>Jeremie</hi> calls, a <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſleep</hi>) would be to thoſe tormented ſoules. It would be, as <hi>Juſtine Martyr</hi> calls it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>an unexpected gaine.</hi> For, never did any condemned wretch at the houre of death ſo much deſire life, as the Damned amidſt their everliving torments doe deſire death; ſuch a death, as might deprive them of all manner of beeing: They would moſt willingly ceaſe to Bee, on condition that they might not be thus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. Faction may drive men into ſtrange opinions little leſſe than blaſphemie: ſuch as their's is who affirme, that it is better to be eternally miſerable, than not to be at all. But our Saviour's doctrine will alwaies be true,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.24.</note> that <hi>it had been good for ſuch men, if they had never been borne:</hi> that they never had any beeing at all.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117580:8"/>
               <p>It is in a caſe farre more tolerable, onely in reſpect of the miſeries of this life, that <hi>Job</hi> wiſheth,<note place="margin">Job 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>That he had been as an hidden untimely birth, that he had not been, as Infants which never ſaw light:</hi> Accounting it much better not to have been at all, than to ſuffer the miſeries of this ſhort and tranſitory life. How much more were it to be deſired by the Damned, that they had no beeing at all, than that they ſhould alwaies ſuffer the unſpeakable torments of endleſſe burnings?</p>
               <p>It is not more certaine that I ſpeake, or that you doe heare; than it is ſure that there is ſuch a Damnation of Hell; and that the paines thereof are more dreadfull, than any tongue is able to utter, or any heart to conceive. But the greateſt of all thoſe torments is that which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told you, and doe willingly touch it once againe, to the end that you may alwaies remember it, That after many thouſand millions of ages the Damned are no neerer to the end of their torments, than they were the very firſt minute, that they entered into them. Once into Hell, and never out: Then we cannot, but now <hi>we may Eſcape this Damnation of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="3">III. For, unleſſe there were a poſſibility for them, to whom Chriſt ſpake, to Eſcape this damnation of which He ſpeaketh; He would never have preached this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to them. The end of Chriſt's preaching was the ſame which ought to be of all ours: not to tell men that they are unavoidably damned; but to teach them how they may be ſaved; to ſhew them the meanes, how they <hi>may eſcape</hi> this damnation.</p>
               <p>The manner of ſpeech which Chriſt here uſeth by way of queſtion doth not argue an <hi>abſolute impoſſibility,</hi> but onely a a <hi>great difficulty</hi> to Eſcape this damnation of hell. Although <hi>ſtraight is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and few there be that find it:</hi> yet ſome there are that find it; and our fault it is, and onely ours, if we be not ſome of thoſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117580:9"/>few, who find that way to heaven, and ſo eſcape this dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of hell.</p>
               <p>For, <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved, and to come to the knowledge of the truth:</hi> They are Saint <hi>Paul's</hi> owne words, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. Seing <hi>his will is that all men ſhould be ſaved,</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe he hath not <hi>abſolutely decreed,</hi> that any man ſhould be <hi>peremptorily damned:</hi> Theſe two imply no leſſe than a meere contradiction.</p>
               <p>God forbid that Satan ſhould ſo farre poſſeſſe the heart of any man, as to perſwade him, that it were impoſſible for him to Eſcape the damnation of hell; this were to make him caſt off all the meanes, which God in his word hath preſcribed to that end. This were to make all the exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, admonitions, promiſes and threatnings of God to be of none effect. For, why ſhould God propoſe unto men, or why ſhould they uſe the meanes of obtaining ſalvation, if it be not poſſible for them to Eſcape damnation.</p>
               <p>God's promiſes are true, and his threatnings ſerious: As he is not mocked, ſo neither doth he mock any man, when he tells him,<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.28.</note> that if he reſent, and <hi>turne from all his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die.</hi> God doth not will death, not the death of any man, not the death of a wicked man. Thoſe Infidels that will not believe God upon his word, may heare him confirme this truth with an oath, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way and live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is Gods wil that all men ſhould Eſcape this damnation: that ſome Eſcape it, is his great mercy: but that many fall into it,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.13. Verſ. 16.</note> is from their owne hard and impenitent heart, which will not lay hold on Chriſt, and uſe thoſe meanes, which God mercifully affordeth unto them. <hi>God made not death, neither hath he pleaſure in the deſtruction of the living. But ungodly men with their works and words called it unto them.</hi> And as for Hell, it was prepared, not for us men<note n="*" place="margin">Primarily.</note>, but for the Devil and his Angels. It is the obſervation of one of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117580:9"/>the antient Fathers upon thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. So generall, that it is contradicted by none of them all.</p>
               <p>But I may ſeeme to wrong this Chriſtian auditory; in that I inſiſt upon the confirmation of that which I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded none here will, becauſe I am ſure none ſhould deny. This I dare aſſure you confidently, that there is not any one of you, to whom I ſpeake, but <hi>may Eſcape</hi> this damnation; if he will uſe the meanes requiſite thereunto: And that is the next and laſt particular, of which I am to treat: <hi>How we may Eſcape, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="4">IV. I doubt not but that this point of doctrine, will be glad tidings to every Chriſtian's heart: Every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth (as every Chriſtian ought to believe) that there is a Hell, would be very willing to eſcape the eternall damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
               <p>And the firſt meanes to eſcape this damnation Hell is this:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Stedfaſtly to believe that there is ſuch a place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> where all wicked and impenitent Sinners ſhall be puniſhed eternally.</p>
               <p>Let it not ſeeme ſtrange to any, that I propoſe the <hi>beliefe</hi> of Hell as a meanes to avoid it. For, certainly if men did ſtedfaſtly <hi>believe</hi> that there are eternall torments prepared for the wicked, they would not live thus wickedly. It was a juſt complaint of one of the Heathen, that in his time, when wickedneſſe did greatly abound, the opinion of Hell was accounted as a Fable onely to affright little Children. And it is to be doubted, that even among them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Name of Chriſt, there are too many, who would willingly perſwade themſelves, that the torments of Hell are but a fiction, a thing invented onely to deterre men from ſinne. For, can we imagine that a foule Adulterer, a prophane Swearer, a common Drunkard, a covetous Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or any the like wicked man, who perſeveres in his knowne ſinnes, would commit thoſe ſinnes, if he did <hi>ſeriouſly believe</hi> that he ſhould ſuffer ſuch puniſhment? Would he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117580:10"/>incurre the eternall paines of Hell, for a moment of ſinfull pleaſure? Doubtleſſe he would <hi>not commit</hi> the one, if he <hi>did believe</hi> the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Eſpecially if he did <hi>Often and ſeriouſly Meditate upon it:</hi> Which is a ſecond and that a very ſoveraigne meanes to Eſcape this damnation of Hell. For, certainly (as I have told you already) a very effectuall meanes to prevent our deſcending into Hell in body and ſoule, is, <hi>Often to deſcend thither in our thoughts and meditations.</hi> He that doth ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe, that there is ſuch a place of torment prepared for the wicked, and alſo frequently <hi>meditate</hi> upon the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall horror of that place, can hardly commit that finne, which ſhould bring him into that place of intolerable and endleſſe torment.</p>
               <p>It was the juſt complaint of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his time, and it will fit ours much better: <hi>Nemo futurorum metum cogitat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>No man doth thinke upon the feare of thoſe things that are to come, the day of the Lord and the anger of God: No man doth conſider the puniſhments, which ſhall be inflicted on the wicked, and the eternall torments, which are appointed for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers. Which our conſcience would fear, if it did believe: Becauſe it doth not at all believe it, it doth not feare: But if it did believe it, it would beware of it: if it would take heed of it, it would eſcape it.</hi> Where you ſee, that a good meanes to eſcape Hell, is to believe, that there is ſuch a place of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible torments, and often to think upon the horror thereof. This, if any thing will prevaile with us, is moſt likely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine us from ſinne, and conſequently preſerve us from damnation. For, I am ſtrongly of Saint <hi>Bernard's</hi> opinion; that nothing doth preſerve us ſo free from ſinne, as doth the Love of God and the Feare of Hell. As one naile doth drive out another: ſo the fire of <hi>Hell</hi> doth oftentimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the fire of <hi>luſt;</hi> and ſuffers us not to commit that, which would make us liable to eternall damnation.</p>
               <p>If we would often call to mind and ſeriouſly ponder in our hearts that queſtion which is asked by ſome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117580:10"/>
                  <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with the devouring ſire? Who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings?</hi> It is very likely that we would uſe all poſſible meanes to eſcape that <hi>devouring fire,</hi> thoſe <hi>everlaſting burnings?</hi> And let no man thinke it an irkſome thing to <hi>meditate</hi> upon ſo diſmall a ſubject. It is much better to be <hi>troubled with the thought</hi> of it here, than to be <hi>ſtung with the torment</hi> of it hereafter. For, if it be grievous to <hi>thinke on it</hi> onely, how intolerable will be to <hi>ſuffer it</hi> for ever? <hi>Thinke</hi> upon Hell often, and you will not ſo often commit ſinne. By frequent and ſerious <hi>meditation</hi> upon Hell you are in a right way to avoid ſinne, and by avoiding ſinne to eſcape damnation.</p>
               <p>Often preſent unto your ſelves the dreadful countenance of that juſt and angry Judge, who will condemne all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Sinners to ſuffer eternall torments. Thinke upon that countenance, at which the Angels themſelves cannot chuſe but tremble. Conſider the unſpeakable paines of that <hi>devouring fire,</hi> thoſe <hi>everlaſting burnings:</hi> and above all conſider that they are everlaſting, that ſhall never have an end: <hi>Meditate</hi> upon theſe things often, and <hi>conſider</hi> them ſeriouſly, and this <hi>meditation</hi> will prove a ſoveraigne preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative againſt ſinne and damnation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But you muſt be <hi>carefull</hi> to uſe your utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>to eſchew all the allurements of the Devill, whereby he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to draw men into perdition:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 13.24.</note> and <hi>ſtrive</hi> you muſt <hi>to enter in at the ſtraight gate,</hi> which leadeth into the kingdome of heaven, how ſtraight ſo ever it be. Let not the honours, wealth of pleaſures of this world divert you from that way, and draw you into that broad way, which leadeth unto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. This is a moſt profitable and neceſſary meanes to avoid the damnation of Hell; when we ſhun all thoſe things which are likely to bring us thither. He that will eſcape the eternall torments of the life to come, muſt carefully avoid the unlawfull pleaſures of this preſent life.</p>
               <p>I thinke it not unprofitable in this point to relate unto a diſcurſe, which I have read, between a Frier and a young
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117580:11"/>Gallant: The young Man ſeeing the Frier go bare-foot and to looke pale with faſting, ask'd him, <hi>why he did undergo all this auſterity, and deprive himſelfe of the pleaſures of this world?</hi> The Frier anſwered him, <hi>that he did it to the end, that he might thereby appeaſe God's anger, and to eſcape the eternall torments of Hell. But,</hi> ſaies the young Man, <hi>what if there be no Hell: art not thou then a great foole, who doſt do and ſuffer all this to no purpoſe?</hi> To which the Frier replies; <hi>But if there be, as I verily believe there is a Hell, a place of unſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and endleſſe torments, is not your worſhip a greater Foole, who to enjoy the ſinfull pleaſures of this world for a ſhort ſeaſon, doe hazard the eternall damnation of your body and ſoule?</hi> And indeed what greater madneſſe can there be, than to refuſe the ſhort paines, which are to be undergone by thoſe that will live godly in this life, and chuſe the everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prepared for the Devil? Thinke upon the grievous paines of Hell; and you will think no paine grievous, which is undergone for the love of God and a good conſcience. The aſſured hope which we have to eſcape that dreadfull torment, will make all the exerciſes of religion, how irkſome ſoever to fleſh and blood, to ſeeme light unto us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth meanes to eſcape the damnation of Hell, is <hi>To keep our ſelves in the unity of God's Church:</hi> that Church which we believe to be the Holy and Catholique. Holy, in the practice of all godlineſſe; Catholique, in the unanimous profeſſion of the true faith: Whereof the one excludes all prophane and wicked Livers, the other all Schiſmaticks and Miſ-believers. In this Church and the communion thereof if we preſerve our ſelves, <hi>by living righteouſly and believing aright,</hi> we need not feare but that we may and ſhall eſcape the damnation of Hell.</p>
               <p>Of this Church, not of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation whatſoever, but of this Holy and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church is Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> to be underſtood; <hi>That he cannot have God for his Father, who hath not the Church for his Mother:</hi> and that other; <hi>That without the Church there
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117580:11"/>is no ſalvation.</hi> As at the firſt deſtruction of the world for ſinne, all that were found out of the Arke periſhed by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So at the laſt day all that ſhall be found out of the Church (whereof the Arke was a type) ſhall be deſtroyed by everlaſting fire. But, as many as ſhall be found within the Church ſhall be free from the damnation of Hell. Of this Holy and Catholique Church is that promiſe to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, which our Saviour made, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>That the gates of Hell ſhall not prevaile against it:</hi> neither againſt it, nor any member of it. Whoſoever doth abide in the unity of this Church, ſhall never come into the condemnation of eternall fire.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And all this by meanes of <hi>Faith in Christ and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:</hi> who for our ſakes deſcended into Hell, that we might never come there. For, by vertue of Chriſt's death, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and his glorious reſurrection from death and hell, we are made free from the one and the other; both from the power of death and the torments of hell. If we be members of Chriſt, we ſhall together with Him partake of eternall bliſſe and glory. Becauſe,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſoules of the righteous are in the hand of God, and there ſhall no torment touch them.</hi> No tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall touch them, becauſe they are the members of Chriſt: who hath ſatisfied for us, whatſoever we ſhould have ſuffered: <hi>Who hath the keyes of Hell and of death;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 1.18.</note> that neither Death nor Hell ſhould prevaile over us.</p>
               <p>Let us ſeriouſly conſider theſe things in our hearts: That there are eternall torments prepared for all thoſe, that ſinne againſt God, and repent not of thoſe ſins.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This very conſideration is a ſufficient motive to work is us a (1) <hi>Serious</hi> and (2) <hi>Speedy Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Serious,</hi> conſidering we believe the torments of Hell to be, as they are indeed <hi>endleſſe</hi> and <hi>intolerable.</hi> If we ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe and ſeriouſly conſider this; we will not eſteem any thing of this world, which may endanger our eſtate of eternity. Let them take care of this preſent life, and of the tranſitory goods of this world, who have no hope to enjoy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117580:12"/>the life to come, and the everlaſting pleaſures thereof. Let them take their pleaſure in this world, who have no hope to eſcape the paines of the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. So likewiſe will it worke in us a <hi>Speedy Repentance;</hi> not ſuffering us to delay the time; leſt the damnation due to our ſinnes ſhould overtake us, before we have repented of them. Conſidering, that we cannot begin too ſoone to prevent that which ſhall never have an end. This ſhould be our firſt &amp; only care, that we may eſcape this damnation: We ſhould regard nothing in compariſon of this. We ſhould be carefull of falling into this fire; that we ſhould beware of every action that we doe, every word that we ſpeak, and every thought that we thinke; leſt it ſhould prove unto us an occaſion of falling into ſinne, and ſo into hell.</p>
               <p>If of all the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> there ſhould but one onely man ſuffer theſe horrible torments, of which we have ſpoken; yet ought we to be exceeding carefull, every one of us ought to beware, leſt it might be <hi>his lot</hi> to ſuffer them. How much more carefull ought we to be, ſeing the number of thoſe that periſh is infinite, and few there be that ſhall be ſaved? Seing ſcarce one of ten thouſand ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape this damnation, what manner of men ought we to be in all holy and vertuous converſation?<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.18.</note> For, <hi>If the Righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and Sinners appeare?</hi> Ought not every one of us (us, who are guilty of many and grievous ſinnes, ought not we) to uſe all poſſible meanes to eſcape this damnation? Ought we not earneſtly to enquire with the young man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.16. <hi>What good thing ſhall I doe, that I may have eternall life?</hi> With the Goaler, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.30. <hi>What muſt I doe to be ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suppoſe this queſtion to be propoſed to us, any of us in particular, as it was to the Scribes and Phariſees: <hi>How can Ye?</hi> ye Adulterers, ye Drunkards, ye Blaſphemers, ye co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, ye malitious, ye envious, ye Schiſmaticks, ye Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ye Hypocrites, ye ſacrilegious Robbers of God and his Church, ye that are guilty of theſe many and grievous ſins,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117580:12"/>or of any of them, or of any like unto them. <hi>How can Ye Eſcape this Damnation of Hell?</hi> Impoſſible it is for you to eſcape theſe torments, which I have deſcribed; unleſſe ye uſe the meanes, which I have preſcribed unto you.</p>
               <p>Now God of his infinite mercy aſſiſt us with his Holy Spirit, that we may uſe thoſe meanes, and ſo eſcape this damnation. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1649.</p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
